Hello and welcome to another video with
it's Dr. Dan and here what we're going
to be doing is introducing Lewis
structures. So for Lewis structures it
comes down to just a set of simple steps
in order to be able to draw how
different elements are covealently
bonding together. So we're going to be
focused on coalent molecules, meaning
that we're going to be looking at the
sharing of electrons. So how do we go
about doing that? So the first thing
that we're going to really be trying to
look at here is we're going to be trying
to count the total number of valence
electrons. So it's really helpful if
you're using a periodic table to be able
to go through that and know your
different trends for counting veence
electrons. Um the next thing we're going
to be doing is choosing the center of
attention. So which atom out of all of
them can bond to the most things. So for
example, carbon has four veence
electrons meaning that if it wants to
fulfill the octet rule so to have a
total of eight electrons, it needs to
bond to four things. So that's four
bonds. It's so it's usually the center
of attention for most structures. Um
other things that we are going to do is
then place all the elements around your
central atom. Draw the skeletal
structure of it. So using single bonds
to show that. So we'll go through that.
Um next we'll assign all the remaining
electrons to make sure everything is
happy and has satisfied octets. And
we'll go through a couple of different
steps showing that. So all right, how
let's get started. How do we go through
trying to um trying to do this? So, I
have a periodic table here ready to go
just like I was recommending. We'll zoom
in and out of that just so we can kind
of show uh how do we pick the different
different structures. So, let's do
something that's normal to all of us,
something that we probably drink every
single day. So, why don't we start with
water? What is the balance or the le
structure for water? So the first thing
is is we have to count our valence
electrons. So if you remember going back
to our periodic table really that comes
down to a very simple trend for how to
count valence electrons. So if we look
at our main group elements so that means
the two side columns. So the two on the
left here and then the six on the right.
These are our main groups. The numbering
is as simple as looking at the Roman
numerals on top. So we have 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 veence electrons for all these
different species. So if we have
hydrogen, hydrogen is right over here.
So that's on column number one. So
that's going to be one veence electron.
Oxygen is over here on six. So that's
going to have six veence electrons. So
when we are writing that down and
drawing that structure out, we're going
to show that our hydrogen has one veence
electron
and there are two of them. So make sure
we keep that in mind. And then we also
have our oxygen which has six veence
electrons and there are one of them. So
when we do that little simple math for
ourselves, it'll be 6 + 2. So this tells
you that okay well we're we have eight
veence electrons in total. So one of the
why is that important to count them
every time? Well when you're going
through the process of drawing these
structures you want to make sure you
have the same number of valence
electrons that you start with and that
you end with. You don't want to make
some crazy structure. So let's write
that down for ourselves. Same veence
electrons. Um so remember that for later
for yourself is have that number. So out
of these which one can make more bonds?
So remember we want to satisfy the octet
rule which means that we want to have a
total of eight electrons. So if we have
that total of eight electrons um in this
particular structure and let me move
that over because I realize that's
getting cut off is
how are we going to be showing those
eight electrons?
Well, oxygen can make two bonds to
fulfill eight. So that's two bonds.
Hydrogen can make one bond. So what that
means is that all right, oxygen can make
more. So that's going to be our center
atom. So when we are doing that, we are
going to take that center atom. We're
going to write its six veence electrons
around it. So we have 1 2 3 4 5 6. Now
we are going to put the hydrogens's
around it. So we have our hydrogens like
so. Each one has one veence electron and
we are going to connect them with a
single bond. Now we want to check does
everything have a happy octet. So with
oxygen one thing how can we count them?
So if we kind of zoom in here for
ourselves we can see that it has 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 veence electrons that are being
shared with oxygen. So, it's happy. Now,
what about hydrogen? Hydrogen's a little
strange. If we kind of look at a
hydrogen, we only see that there's one,
two. Is that happy? Well, the answer is
yes, it is. So, if you remember looking
at our periodic table and you go back to
veence electron or or electron
configuration from probably a long time
ago when you first covered electrons in
your chemistry class, hydrogen is 1 s1
for its electron configuration.
And when it's on that second row, it can
only go up to 1 s2. Meaning that
hydrogen only needs two electrons. So,
hydrogen
follows a duet rule, meaning it only
needs two. It only takes two to dance.
Oxygen is going to be the octet rule.
They are both happy in this case. So, we
can give them little check marks. We
have our Lewis structure. So, if we want
to clean that up for ourselves, we can.
We can write hydrogen, write the little
lone pairs for for that, and draw
another hydrogen. So whenever we have
little dots like this, these are
referred to as lone pair electrons. And
you can see that we have two sets of
them. We also have our single bonds.
So that's two electrons and the single
bond represents two electrons being
shared. Okay? So those are being shared
between those two elements. Okay? So
let's try a different one. What if I ask
you to what if we do another common
element? What if we do something that we
breathe in? So oxygen. So if we breathe
in oxygen, how would we show that Lewis
dot structure? Well, same idea, right?
We count the number of valence
electrons. So if you remember from last
time, oxygen had six veence electrons.
So there are two of them. So that means
this whole entire species is going to
have 12 electrons. So being there's only
two of them, we're not going to have a
central atom because they're both just
bonding to two. In order for something
to be central, it has to be bonding to
two or more. So why don't we write that
down? Central atoms, and you can have
more than one, have to be bound to two
or more species.
And when I say species, I mean atoms.
Okay. All right. So if we have oxygen,
we will write that we have an oxygen
that has six veence electrons around it.
Just like so. We will draw another
oxygen. We will write its six veence
electrons around it. We will connect
them with a single bond. Right? So we'll
start off there. Now are they happy?
looking at them. Do you count eight
veence electrons around each oxygen? So,
if we kind of like zoom in on this,
well, we can try counting them. So, if I
do, let's count the ones for the oxygen
with the purple electrons. So, when we
do that side, we see we have 1 2 3 4 5 6
7. So, it's not happy. Well, if you
remember from before, I had one step for
how to fulfill these. So once you assign
all of your veence electrons, you're
going to use double and triple bonds to
fulfill everything until it's all happy.
So we're going to be doing a double bond
in this case. So when we have a double
bond,
as you can see, both sides have this
extra electron. They're both going to
move and interact with the bonds. So,
we're going to move both of those to the
middle here.
We're going to erase them. So, we still
have them on this side, but instead now
what we're going to be doing is making
an additional bond between the two
atoms. So, when that happens, we now
have a double bond. So, that allows us
to have our eighth electron now being
shared. So we now have a happy octet for
each species. So oxygen is going to have
a double bond. Now what other species
can we do? What else do you breathe in?
What else part of air? Well, okay, you
have oxygen, nitrogen. So why don't we
try nitrogen? How would you go about
doing that one? Well, how many valence
electrons does nitrogen have? Let's go
to our periodic table. And we can see
that all right, nitrogen's on column
five here. So what that's going to tell
you is that all right it has five veence
electrons. So when we do that
we will write our nitrogen
draw its five veence electrons.
So you can see how many bonds can
nitrogen make. You can see that it wants
to make three bonds because it has three
electrons that are by themselves. They
want to they want to make a friend. So,
if we're doing N2,
this might give you a hint of what the
structure is going to be if it wants to
make three bonds. Well, the first thing
we're going to do is we're going to bind
two of them.
Is it happy? Well, right now it only has
each one only has six electrons, so
definitely not. So, what we can then do
is is redraw some of these and move
them.
So if I move two of them here and here,
I can connect them.
I'm using a different color. We can
reconnect them.
So now we have two. Now notice if I kind
of count these, right? We have 1 2 3 4 5
6 7. Still not happy. So we can add
another one and make a triple bond.
So when we do a triple bond,
that's going to move another electron
over to the middle and connect them as
well. So when we do that, now we have
how many electrons being shared? There
are six. Oops, that's a little too big.
We have six electrons now being shared.
Six shared electrons.
When we did a double bond earlier with
oxygen,
we had we had a total of four shared
electrons.
So with every bond or every line you're
drawing, you're adding more electrons
that are being shared. So with that with
that, there's a small little tip here
that you can try to remember for how to
quickly draw these. So one thing you
might have noticed is that depending on
the number of veence electrons there are
bond trends that we can see here as
well. So if you remember oxygen had six
veence electrons. So how many bonds did
it make? It made a total of two bonds.
Well nitrogen it had five veence
electrons. So it can make three bonds.
We didn't draw a carbon but carbon like
we said before had four veence
electrons. So that can make four bonds.
So, if you kind of look at this trend
that's going, if you go to the right, it
goes 432.
Well, you can probably take a guess that
it's 4321.
So, there's a trend here for yourself
for remembering the different bond
trends. So, if you kind of write these
down for yourself, it makes Lewis
structures really quick to do. So, let's
just do a couple more examples for with
each other just before we kind of sign
off and see how we do. So what if I do
what we breathe out? What if I do CO2?
How would we draw that out? So the first
thing we got to do is figure out how
many veence electrons can they make. So
if you remember carbon is on that fourth
column. So what that means is it has
four veence electrons, nitrogen 5,
oxygen 6 1. So that means that carbon is
going to be making four bonds and has
four veence electrons. So let's draw
that first. So we have carbon. We have
our four dots.
We have our oxygen which had a total of
six dots.
And one little tip, as you can see, I'm
I'm always lining up the single
electrons with each other because you
want to connect them all with single
bonds first. It makes a little bit
easier on yourself and a little a lot
less erasing when you are doing these
different bonds. So, we fill in our six
veence electrons on each of these. We'll
connect them all with a single bond.
Now, going back to our trends, how do
you know the structure? Well, carbon
wants to make four bonds. Each oxygen
wants to make two. So, you can maybe
take a guess. If each oxygen wanted to
make two bonds,
carbon wants to make four
and two.
Well, what can satisfy that is your
double and triple bonds. So, if I move
one of these to here in the middle,
notice how
on the left side now oxygen is now
making two bonds. It's happy. And in the
process, we get rid of one of those lone
electrons. We'll do the same thing here
on the other one.
and we will make the different bonds.
So, notice how we have four bonds, two
bonds, two bonds. It makes a perfect
structure for CO2. All the electrons are
accounted for. Um, we could count them
all. We could see they're all here. Um,
when you're going through that going
through that process. So, let's do
another. What if we do NH3?
What is going to be your central atom?
Well, what can make the most bonds?
Well, if we look at our little list,
nitrogen can make three. Hydrogen, which
is hidden over here, can only make one.
So, nitrogen is going to be your central
atom. So, if we do nitrogen, we know
from before it has five veence
electrons. So, we have 1 2 3 4 5. Then,
we'll fill it in with all the
hydrogens's all around it.
So we'll put hydrogens on all sides
where the single dots are. We'll put
dots here, here, and here. And now we
will connect them all with a single
bond. And now you can see we can count
and double check for ourselves. Do we
have the right number of electrons?
Well, if I like take a look at that, we
have for nitrogen, we have 1, two, and
those are the two for hydrogen as well.
3 4 5 6 7 8. So everything is accounted
for in our structure. We have all of our
electrons and we're making them all.
Let's try something a little bit harder
in terms of trying to figure out
structures.
So what if I give you C H
L as a structure and you're like what
the heck is that? How do we figure out
what the structure is? Well, it's
simple. We can try to just figure out
what the number of total bonds for each
species. So, if we go up to have our
chart up here, well, we can label
everything for how many bonds it can
make. You know that carbon can make
four, hydrogen's one, oxygen's two,
chlorine is also one. So, what's going
to be your central atom? It's going to
be carbon. It can make the most bonds.
So, that's going to be the center of
attention. So if that's the case, well,
all right, that's our bond. So we'll
write that down. Carbon is going to be
in the middle with its four veence
electrons.
And now what we're going to do is we're
going to space out the other species on
all sides. So let's start with hydrogen.
So hydrogen has one veence electron.
We'll connect that to carbon. Okay. So
hydrogen's happy. We don't have to worry
about that.
Now let's put chlorine in chlorine. And
why am I skipping oxygen? Chlorine only
can bond to one thing as well. It has
seven veence electrons. And we can
double check the periodic table. So we
can see chlorine is right here. It it
needs uh it has it's on column seven. So
it needs one bond. So if that's the
case, why don't we do that one real
quick? So we'll have chlorine down here.
We have 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. We'll connect
that. Now, how many bonds can oxygen
make? Well, if you remember, it can make
two. And there's still two single
electrons that are available over here.
So, being that those are still there,
it's going to be making a double bond.
And you can see that here in a second.
So if I put oxygen in and I put its lone
electrons 1 2 3 4 5 6
we will connect those. Notice how oxygen
still has a single electron that's by
itself. It does not want a single
electron. They want to all be paired. So
we're going to move that and make a
double bond.
Okay. And now we have our happy
structure just like that.
Now let's do one last one. Why don't we
do something with a charge on it? So a
charge. So if I give you CN minus.
Okay. So what does that tell us? So if
you remember from before, if I have a
negative charge, what this tells you
that on this molecule there is a
negative charge located somewhere on it.
It doesn't have to be on the nitrogen.
It could be on the carbon. It's on one
of these species. A negative tells you
you have one extra electron.
A positive tells you you have one less
electron.
Okay? So that means that when we do
this, we're going to have one more
electron. So if carbon has four veence
electrons,
nitrogen has five veence electrons,
we're going to be getting one extra from
the negative charge. So we're going to
have a total of 10 veence electrons.
So let's try and draw it. So let's write
out our species. So if I start with
carbon, carbon we know has four.
Nitrogen has five.
So we'll start by connecting them first
with just a single bond. Notice how
neither are very happy. So one thing
what we'll do is we'll maximize number
of bonds which is three, right? Three is
the ultimate. Also nitrogen can make up
to three bonds as well. So and carbon
can do up to four. So why don't we do
that? We're going to rearrange all these
so that way we can start with a triple
bond.
And we can see that all right well
nitrogen's happy. Nitrogen has six
electrons being shared
and then the two up here. Now how can
carbon be happy? It's has a lone
electron all by it all by itself. What
can it exactly do in that case? Well,
don't forget that we have that one extra
one. So, we can put that in the spot
where it is most needed. So, in that
case, we now have a happy structure. And
the only thing that left to do is being
that there's a charge, we're going to
put brackets around it with a negative
charge just like so. Okay. So, that is
how you can go through and do Lewis
structures. Um, if you need any future
help, please don't hesitate to reach out
and I will be making more videos to
come. All right, this is how we can make
Lewis structures and this has been Dr.
Dan. Please consider hitting that sub
and like button and I hope to see you in
the future. Bye now.
[Music]